BETH: Depending on the level of ability
and skills an individual with autism has,
they can once they gain employment, become
a valued member of a company’s workforce.
They can offer loyalty, dedication and
can be extremely skillful once trained.
They may even have advanced skills to
offer if they are high functioning.
JOE: However, they may find the usual
process of gaining and starting employment
very challenging because of their disorder
and not their ability to do the job.
If they are supported through
the process by both the employer
and their carers, they can find
seeking and gaining employment
easier to navigate and understand.
BETH: The more employers are open to
taking on individuals with autism,
the more they will understand
their needs, and the skills and
expertise they have to offer.
It is important that employers realise
that many individuals with autism do
not see themselves as ‘disabled’ but
‘neurodiverse’ meaning they just look at
life differently, so they can also bring
this original thinking to a job role.
JOE: High functioning individuals can
be very successful in many different
fields including science, research,
finance, banking and the arts.
If employers are more open to looking
at candidates who are on the spectrum,
they have opportunities to make their
workforce more diverse, with a chance
that they may become their best employees.
BETH: Individuals with autism can
be supported by employers offering
paid work placements to see how
individuals fit into their workforce.
This can help them to make any adjustments
that might be needed before offering
a full-time role, and it can give
individuals with autism a step into
employment, to see what it involves
and gain that valuable work experience.
JOE: Making the application process for
individuals with autism, simpler and more
inclusive will help in the beginning.
This can be done by companies
becoming more autism aware,
especially about the skills
individuals with autism have to offer.
Being clear in the job application
and interview process, can support
individuals directly, making it
easier for them to feel that they
have a chance of gaining employment.
BETH: Being aware of sensory
sensitivities and communication
difficulties, can help prepare them
for the differences individuals present
in social interaction, such as in the
interview and job induction phase.
Also going forward to when they accept
a role within a company, their sensory
needs within their working environment.
Little changes and reasonable adjustments
can make a lot of difference to an
individual with autism and can help
them to settle in a job and become
a valued member of the workforce.